Inventory of the Alfred Poninski papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alfred Poninski papers
1917-1942
81037
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoirs, reports, notes, and printed matter relating to Polish-Soviet and Polish-Romanian relations, and to religious persecution in the Soviet Union.
Poninski, Alfred.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1896 June 18 Born in Koscielisko, Posen (Poznan) province, Poland
circa 1910-1914 Attended a gymnasium at Bromberg (Bydgoszcz) and studied law at the University of Berlin
1914 Began work as a journalist
1918 October Appointed press attaché at the Polish legation in Berlin
1919-1920 Assistant in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Warsaw
1921 Married Janina Nowodworska
1921-1926 Served in diplomatic posts in Brussels and Paris
1925 Author, "Les Traditions de la Diplomatie Polonaise," Revue d'Histoire Diplomatique
1926 Author, La Question Polonaise Depuis 1830 Jusqu'à la Grande Guerre
1926-1933 Counselor of legation to the Soviet Union
1935-1941 Counselor of legation to Romania
1941-1942 Consul general, Istanbul, Turkey
1942-1945 Ambassador to China
1946 Moved to Australia
1947-1950 President of the Polish Democratic Society, Sydney
1950-1951 Founding president of the Federal Council of Polish Associations in Australia
1950s Vice-president of the United Council of Migrants and of the New Australians' Cultural Association, and a council-member of the State division of the New Settlers' League of Australia, the Australian Council for International Social Service, and the Australian Institute of International Affairs
1953-1963 Regular contributor, Tygodnik Katolicki, Melbourne
1967-1968 Author, "Poland in the Second War" (series of articles in Wiadomosci Polskie)
1968 March 25 Died, Sydney, Australia
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoirs, reports, notes, and printed matter relating to Polish-Soviet and Polish-Romanian relations, and to religious persecution in the Soviet Union.
Communism and religion.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Romania.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Romania--Foreign relations--Poland.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.; Soviet Union--Religion.; Diplomats--Poland.
- Polish legation, Bucharest, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 1: 1-4)
- "Pro publico bono. Rozwazania polityczne o naszej przyszlosci,", 1941 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- "Le Marechal Pilsudski en Roumanie. Premier voyage" (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Articles and speeches, 1927-1937 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Varia (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Correspondence to the Consulate General in Istanbul, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Polish legation, Moscow
  - Help extended to the deported and imprisoned Polish clergy and correspondence with Cardinal Hlond, 1928-1932 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
  - Materials relating to the persecution of Orthodox and Catholic church in Russia, 1923-1933 (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
  - Court case of Reverend Teofil Skalski, Butyrki prisoner, 1928 January (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Reports relating to the return of King Stanislaus August's remains to Poland, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- "Reminiscences of the Polish Diplomat in Moscow,", 1928 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Polish-Romanian relations between the two world wars (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Anatolia Nowicka: From the history of the Polish Dominican Sisters in Moscow, 1923-1932 (Box-folder 2: 11)